Some legacies must end.
American History X is a drama film directed by Tony Kaye.
Derek Vineyard is paroled after serving 3 years in
prison for killing two African-American men.
Through his brother, Danny Vineyard's narration, we learn that before going to prison, Derek was a skinhead and
the leader of a violent white supremacist gang that committed acts of racial crime throughout L.A.
and his actions greatly influenced Danny.
Reformed and fresh out of prison, Derek severs contact with the gang and becomes
determined to keep Danny from going down the same violent path as he did.
Derek, played by Edward Norton.
Danny, played by Edward Furlong.
Doris, played by Beverly D'Angelo.
Davina, played by Jennifer Lien.
Seth, played by Ethan Suplee.
Stacey, played by Fairuza Balk.
American History X is a 1998 American crime drama film directed by Tony Kaye
(in his feature directorial debut) and written by David McKenna.
The film stars Edward Norton and Edward Furlong as two brothers from Los Angeles
who are involved in the white power skinhead and neo-Nazi movements.
The older brother (Norton) serves three years in prison for voluntary manslaughter, is rehabilitated during
this time, and then tries to prevent his brother (Furlong) from being indoctrinated further.
The supporting cast includes Fairuza Balk, Stacy Keach, Elliott
Gould, Avery Brooks, Ethan Suplee and Beverly D'Angelo.
McKenna wrote the script based on his own childhood and
experiences of growing up in San Diego.
He sold the script to New Line Cinema, which was impressed by the writing.
American History X was Kaye's first directorial role in a feature film.
Budgeted at $20 million, filming took place in 1997.
Before the film's release, Kaye and New Line Cinema were in disagreements about the
final cut of the film, which Norton had played a pivotal role in editing.
The final version was 40 minutes longer than Kaye's 95-minute cut, which resulted in him publicly disowning the
film through dozens of trade paper advertisements, thus negatively affecting his directing career.
Distributed by New Line Cinema, the film was released in the United States on October 30, 1998 in limited theaters and
received a wide theatrical release on November 20, 1998, grossing $23.9 million against a $20 million budget.
American History X was critically praised, with Norton and Furlong's
performances and the film's message drawing acclaim.
Norton received an Academy Award nomination for Best Actor.
The film has also been used for educational purposes in
the United States and in other countries.
A follow-up, African History Y, with Kaye returning as director and
starring Djimon Hounsou, was in active development as of 2020.
The film explores themes of prison, neo-nazism,
rape, skinhead, sibling relationship.
The tone is dark and emotional.